<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Rome, Spaine, Palermo, Geneuæ and France With the miserable state of the citty of Paris, and the late yeelding vppe of sundrie towns of great strength, vnto the king. Translated out of Italian and French into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11026</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106067</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841792</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841792</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11026)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1333:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Rome, Spaine, Palermo, Geneuæ and France With the miserable state of the citty of Paris, and the late yeelding vppe of sundrie towns of great strength, vnto the king. Translated out of Italian and French into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 leaves : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by J. Wolfe?] for Thomas Nelson, and are to be sold by William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Only leaves 2-3 are foliated.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rome (Italy) --  History --  1420-1798 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6399:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Newes FROM ROME, Spaine, Palermo, Geneuae, and France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the miſerable ſtate of the Citty <hi>of Paris, and the late yeelding vppe of ſundrie Towns of great ſtrength, vnto the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Italian and French into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for Thomas Nelſon, and <hi>are to be ſold by William Wright. 1590.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6399:2"/>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6399:2"/>
            <head>Newes from Rome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is credibly reported by Letters from Chiauenna that there was one of the Famelie of Lucemburge, a Papiſt by profeſſion, and yet a ſeruaunt to the French King, paſſed through Chia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna, with thrée ſcore horſe, and ſtaied there one day. And the next day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, hee departed from thence to Zappei de Briga towards Venice. He goeth in the behalfe of the houſe of Burbon: from ſundry the chéefe of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of Fraunce, to deliuer a meſſage to the Pope, and to haue conference with him and the Princes of Italy, for the firme eſtabliſhing of <hi>Henry de Borbon</hi> King of Nauarre, now the lawfull French King: vnder whoſe obedience they are willing to liue. Which thing hee very boldly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched vnto the Popes face, and told him that they ſought to haue it confirmed with quietneſſe. Adding further that if the Pope and thoſe Princes of Italy would not allowe therof, that they would defend the ſame with fire and ſword. And hazarde their landes and liuings in maintenance of his right. Wherevpon the Pope after due conſideration ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, gaue aunſwere to the Meſſenger, viz. That fore much as hee ſaith he is lawfully deſcended thereunto. And that the chiefe States and Potentates of Germany are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to defend him for the recouerie of his ſaide right. That
<pb facs="tcp:6399:3"/>he would not any more ſende ayde to trouble and vexe him, as heretofore hee hath done: ſo as the King would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge himſelfe eſtabliſhed therein by the Popes meanes. And in ſo doing and yéelding vnto ſome ſuch Popiſhe conditions as the Pope would deliuer him in writing: he would therein further him to the vttermoſt (whereto this Meſſenger made aunſwere that he knew certainly, that the King would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer condeſcended thereunto.) Whereat the Pope replied ſaying: That were it not that the King is a <hi>Hugonite</hi> by profeſſion: hee worthely deſerueth to beare thys title. Viz. <hi>The great Caeſar of the World.</hi> With which glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Title he offered to grace and honour the King, ſo as he would chaunge his Religion.</p>
            <p>IN the Citty of Rome, there is an olde auncient Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment long ſince erected of ſtone, and it is called <hi>Paſquill:</hi> whereon many notable thinges are from time to time ſet vppe in the diſgrace of the Pope of Rome. Vppon which ſaide Piller, there was ſette vppe ſoone after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of this Champian: thrée ſeuerall pictures, either of them being contrarie to the other.</p>
            <p>The firſt picture was as it is here liuely pourtraghed forth Viz. Firſt the Pope ſet out gorgiouſlie in his Robes and triple Crowne: and a ſtraunger holding him by the beard, with a dagge ſet cloſe to his breſt pronouncing this ſentence vnto him: viz.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Redde Rationem villicationis tuae.</q>
            <p>Which being ſeene to the Common people made them greatlye to murmur and bée of ſundry imaginations. Some were of this opinion, that it pretended the murdering of the Pope, or ſome treaſon to his holineſſe: others imagined, that it propheſied the fall of the Popes kingdome, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the Antichriſtian Religion and ſtate of Rome,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6399:3"/>and others ſuppoſed it to bee done onely in the deriſion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Whereuppon ſome fauourer of Chriſtian Religion in the Cittie of Rome, that durſt not openly bee knowen, wrotte certaine verſes vppon eyther of thoſe ſeuerall Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures: and after ſcattered them in the ſtreetes of Rome, where ſoone after ſpéedy ſearche was made for the Author of them, but he coulde not by any meanes be found out.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>pope in his regalia being threatened by a commoner</figDesc>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </figure>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:6399:4"/>
               <l>Thou Pope that doeſt for gold, deceaue full many ſoules.</l>
               <l>And ſéekeſt nought at all, but ſpoile of Chriſtians blood,</l>
               <l>Fall downe before thy God, whom thou doeſt ſtill offend,</l>
               <l>And let Repentance be, the ſtaffe of all thy ſtay.</l>
               <l>Els ſhalt thou ſoone perceiue, Gods wrath is on thy head.</l>
               <l>Vnto thy charge preache truth, caſt of thy paltry traſh,</l>
               <l>Thy Maſſes and thy Markes of plaine Idolatry,</l>
               <l>Séeke not to blinde thoſe men, that doe thy folly ſée,</l>
               <l>But of thy wicked life, ſée iuſt account thou make,</l>
               <l>Gainſt God doe not rebell, nor thoſe whom he annoints,</l>
               <l>But ſhed forth briniſh teares, for all thy déedes amis.</l>
               <l>Els ſhalt thou bée cut off, and kingdome troden downe,</l>
               <l>By him that now in France, of right doth were the crown.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <p>THe ſecond Picture before recited was in this manner. There was Pictured forth the King of Spaine lying in his bedde ſore ſicke: and a Phiſitian ſtanding before him, who taking the King by the hand and féeling of his powlees: ſaith vnto him. Viz.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Durabit tempore Curto.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>the ailing king of Spain attended by a physician</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6399:5"/>
The vearſes made vpon that Picture were theſe.<lb/>
               <q>
                  <l>Blind King what doſt thou mean to bath thy hands in blood</l>
                  <l>Of Innocents, and ſuch as guiltleſſe be,</l>
                  <l>Thou couetſt to obtaine the glorie of this world,</l>
                  <l>Which is like ſléeting Snow that melteth in the Sunne:</l>
                  <l>Thy golde doth thée beſot, and God thou doeſt forget,</l>
                  <l>Thou thirſteſt after that which thou ſhalt neuer winne:</l>
                  <l>Thy kingdome is too large, and that doth thée bewitch,</l>
                  <l>Thou aimeſt ful at France, yet doeſt thou miſſe the marke,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thou woldſt therby procure ſwéet Englands harm.</l>
                  <l>Well maiſt thou ſend to ſeas, thy ſhipping tall and huge,</l>
                  <l>To doe thy neighbour hurt, and gaine thy ſelfe no good:</l>
                  <l>But when thou ſo haſt done, thy ſelfe if ſo thou liue,</l>
                  <l>Shalt ſée and ſaie with me, that God is ſore diſpleaſd,</l>
                  <l>And bids thée be content, thou haſt not long to liue:</l>
                  <l>Séeke therefore for thy end, and ſet thy ſoule at reſt:</l>
                  <l>So ſhalt thou liue for aie, elſe die with great vnreſt.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <p>The third and laſt picture was in this manner, viz. The Citie of Geneua defended by the hande of almightie God, (though aſſaulted by the Duke of Sauoy) was deliuered from daunger of the Dukes forces: and hee forced to flie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie naked, looking backe vpon the ſayde Citie of Geneua, and crieth out ſaying,</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">Neſsio amplius quo vadam.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>the Duke of Savoy fleeing the city of Geneva</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6399:6"/>
The verſes written on the third Picture were theſe.<lb/>
               <q>
                  <l>Thou Sauoy Duke that headlong ſéemſt to runne</l>
                  <l>To ſpoile a Citie of no ſmal account,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wals and gates are kept by God himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Who bids thée backe or he will daunt thée ſo</l>
                  <l>As greatly ſhall returne to thy vnreſt,</l>
                  <l>Retire thou thence, and ſay as other did,</l>
                  <l>When ſeuen ſtout Kings by force did it beſſiege,</l>
                  <l>God doth and will defend it ſtill from harme.</l>
                  <l>It is not force of Canon can do good</l>
                  <l>To winne thy will of that faire maiden towne,</l>
                  <l>Shoote thou ſtrong bullets, it for to diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>They will rebound euen backe vnto thy ſelfe</l>
                  <l>Retire for ſhame, and if thou manage armes,</l>
                  <l>Beſtow thy force gaynſt them that wil thée feare,</l>
                  <l>Euen ſuch I meane as fight againſt the Lord,</l>
                  <l>And dayly ſéeke his Goſpell to deface,</l>
                  <l>But if thou be of that diſloyall minde,</l>
                  <l>And wilt not pray to God to pardon thée,</l>
                  <l>And ſo repent thée of thy former miſſe,</l>
                  <l>Then flie from God. Geneua ſure is his.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <p>Theſe Pictures and Vearſes did ſo farre incenſe the Pope with all the fraternitie of Friers, Monkes and Abbey lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in Rome, that they fell in a rage, curſing and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with bell, booke, and candle, the Deuiſer, Painter and Author of thoſe pictures and vearſes, and did oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues agaynſt the authors thereof, ſwearing to purſue them to death if euer they were knowen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Newes from Spaine is.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:6399:7"/>
            <p>THat the King is ſickly, verie weake and wonderouſlie gréeued with his great loſſes of men &amp; munition which he hath ſuſtained within theſe two yéeres, as wel within his owne dominions, as alſo on the coaſts of England and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France and Flanders. He was lately complotting of a new intended miſchiefe, and with ſome conuenient ſpéede pretended a new Inuaſion for England, whereto hee made great preparation: and to that purpoſe ſent ſundrie traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous perſons ſecretly into England, being ſeminary prieſts, to perſwade the people from their obedience, and to hearten on leude and wicked members, to become fauourers and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates of that Inuaſion. But I thinke no ſubiects in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land hauing ſéene the fruites of the Spaniſh and Popiſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, will now become fauourers of ſuch treaſons, nor be harborers of ſuch traitors. But all things therin doth fall out contrarie to the King of Spaines expectation. For now his owne ſubiects do reſiſt him, and haue made plaine deniall for comming at anie time héereafter in warlike ſort agaynſt the Realme of England: For which cauſe the King of Spain hath put to death ſundrie of his chiefe Captaines and men of good birth and calling, and hath ſworn the death of the Duke of Medina for that cauſe onely. Who in the defence &amp; ſafetie of himſelfe, hath taken an Iland: and ſundrie men of calling and ſouldiers doe take parts with him, and are become verie mutinous againſt the King of Spaine. This Duke de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina was chiefe Generall of the huge armie of Spaniardes that came by ſea to inuade England, when it pleaſed God that the moſt part of them were ſlayne with the ſword and drowned in the ſea: the ſucceſſe of whoſe voyage danted the heartes of all Spaniardes for euer, for inuading this lande. Which as the Almightie hath ſundrie times defended from danger, ſo no doubt but he will ſtill defend and ſupporte the ſame from Turke, Pope, and all other enimes whatſoeuer: which thing is likely by the praiers of good Chriſtians to be the more eaſily compaſſed, for that God is the anchor-holde of Englands hope and ſafetie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:6399:7"/>
            <head>The Newes from Palermo in Cicilie.</head>
            <p>THe certaine newes is, that the Nobilitie of Palermo in Cicilie (being within the dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the king of Spain) haue of late vtterly baniſhed from thence the Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, which hath of long time continued there amongeſt them in verie ſharpe ſort, and was vnto them of Palermo wonderfull grieuous: for ſuch was the ſeuere procéedings of thoſe Inquiſitours, that they would ſpare no man, woman, or childe from the fierie and extreame tortures of death, that did once repine, miſlike, or ſpeake againſt the ſuperſtition of their Friers and idolatrous religion there vſed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Pope, the King of Spaine, and chiefe of the Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, are determined to ſend power thether, and to make warre againſt them, onely to conſtraine them againe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſayd Inquiſition, which they vtterly refuſe to doe, and are all ſworne to the contrarie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Newes from Geneua.</head>
            <p>THat whereas the Citie of Geneua was lately beſieged with a mightie power, brought thether by the Duke of Sauoy, who intended to haue raſed the walls thereof, made a conqueſt of the Citie, and to haue put the Citizens with their wiues and children to the ſworde, yet God be thanked the Citizens haue of late greatly diſcomforted the Dukes power, and cauſed him to remoue his forces further, which is greatly weakned both by ſword and ſicknes, ſo that there is great likelyhood you ſhall heare of the Dukes departure thence verie ſhortly, to the better quietneſſe of the Citizens thereof.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The Newes from France, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of Paris.</head>
            <p>SInce the moſt wonderfull and miraculous worke of God (now bruted in the cars of the world) concerning the great victorie, which he gaue vnto the Chriſtian King <hi>Henrie</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:6399:8"/>
               <hi>Bourbon</hi> (a man for his valor, worthie euerlaſting honor) it is not vnknowen, how after he had purſued the enemie in chaſe full fiue houres and more, and hauing put many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of them to the ſword, though they were more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thrée to one. And after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had put the Duke <hi>de Main</hi> to flight, who ſince hath withdrawen his wife and children from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> vnto <hi>Perone,</hi> that ſundrie towns hath ſince yéelded them ſelues to the mercie of the Kings Maieſtie, as <hi>Vernon, Mentz,</hi> and ſundrie other townes of ſtrength are nowe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently like to be deliuered into his Maieſties handes. Great and likely was the ſigne that God fought for this gracious King, when the night before the battaile hee ſhewed a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous token of victorie to the Kings ſide, namely, by a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched battaile ſéene in the ſkie, where in fight of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand perſons, the leſſer number did ouercome the greater: as it fell out afterward by the Kings ſide, who being but a ſmal number, did put many thouſands of the greater number to the ſword. Since which his good ſucceſſe the King hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the townes of <hi>Corbeyle</hi> and <hi>Melum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corbeyle</hi> was yéelded vp vnto his Maieſtie, but the town of <hi>Melum</hi> hee won by the ſword, where was great effuſion of bloud vpon the enemie. Theſe townes ſtand vpon the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Seine and Laigney vppon the riuer of Marnes, by meanes whereof his Maieſtie hath ſtopt vp all the paſſages of the riuers, ſo as no aide can come vnto them of <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King is at <hi>Clow,</hi> and hauing cut off them at <hi>Paris</hi> from receiuing in anie ſuccour of victuall or otherwiſe: hee hath beſieged <hi>Meos,</hi> and ſendeth ſome of his forces agaynſt Saint <hi>Dennis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pope hath lately ſent his Legate into France, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rge the King of the excommunication which was before pronounced againſt him, ſaying he did it before by falſe infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and hopeth that hee will become a moſt Chriſtian King, and that the Crowne of France doth of right apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto him: and to that purpoſe the Pope hath written to the Cleargie, commanding them to obey and praie for the
<pb facs="tcp:6399:8"/>King vpon paine of his excommunication.</p>
            <p>It is wonderfull to ſée the preſent and gréeuous eſtate of the inhabitants of <hi>Paris,</hi> which City is ſtil with hold from the Kings Maieſtie: yet they haue ſought to the King ſince the departure of the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> to receiue the ſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon conditions, whereto the King will not grant. Hée willeth them to yéeld it vp vnto him as his right, &amp; to ſtand to his mercie, which they haue refuſed to doe, but in the end it wil be the worſe for themſelues.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Paris</hi> doe continue ſéeking to haue ſpéech at <hi>Noyſe,</hi> and doe verily thinke that the Duke <hi>de Maine</hi> will forthwith ſend them ſome great and mightie armie to ſuccor them, beeing now hardly preſſed vp for want of victualles: which thing is vnpoſſible for him to doe, by reaſon of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage which is ſtopt vp, as is before ſpecified. The greater parte of the inhabitants in the Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by their gouernours, that they begin to grewe muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous amongſt themſelues. And the Friers doe dailie preach vnto them, &amp; perſwade them ſtill to reſiſt the King, though it be with the loſſe of their owne liues. Which thing the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſort are conſtrained to conſent vnto, though contrarie to theyr willes, and by reaſon of their want, they are readie to kill one another for victuals.</p>
            <p>Death ſtands there in euerie mans doore, and threatneth their vtter ruine for their wilfull ſtubburnneſſe: and though the pooreſt doe liue in greate penurie, yet the richeſt among them doe make many a hungrie meale. So that nowe it is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon report of euerie French, man in France, They of <hi>Paris</hi> cannot hold out aboue ten or twelue-daies at the moſt Thoſe of <hi>Quillebeufe</hi> haue taken a gally which came from <hi>Roane,</hi> laden with goods of the Duke <hi>de Aumal</hi> and oth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r chiefe men: who had taken thoſe goods from out the houſes of the Kings ſeruants.</p>
            <p>Thus haue you heard how wonderfully God hath defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Kings Maieſtie euen in the daunger of death, where
<pb facs="tcp:6399:9"/>at ſuch time as the enemie made full account to haue ſlayne the King in his flight, he was by Gods prouidence conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the himſelfe, and in the flight compelled to warme himſelfe, and to eſcape in a ſouldiers iacket. This was the will of God, to confound him that ſought the confuſion of his King, and as the ſame God that ſo defended him, hath ſent him ſince towns of great ſtrength, to reſiſt and tame the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſo mightie a ſo, ſo doubtles the ſame God wil ſtil deliuer him from danger, and ſpéedily ſend him his chiefe and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Cities and walled townes yet detained from him: and as well deliuer his chiefeſt enemies into his hande, as alſo to drawe the hearts of all his ſubiects vnto him, maugre the mallice of ſuch miſcreant hel-hounds and deteſtable traitors, or the helliſh crew of the vnholy League, nowe vp in armes agaynſt his Maieſtie, for whoſe ſpéedie confuſion and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, all the true and faithfull fauourers of the King, will continually praie. And for the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and defence of their moſt gracious King and Countrie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6399:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
